Father asks your son
Раз отец спрашивает
Whether to go north
стоит ли идти в поход
Your son dares not say what's right
я не берусь утверждать
Your son only knows
Я лишь знаю
Father shoulders the ancestral state
что отец держит державу на своих плечах
Assumed the throne in times of crisis
принял власть в трудные времена
Turned the tide in an instant
и спас её от краха
Now the north is in constant warfare
На севере постоянные войны
Hundreds of thousands of refugees along the Tianhe
по берегам Тяньхэ сотни тысяч беженцев
Have no home
без крова
Qing Province has troubles
в Цинчжоу мятеж
Floods in the east
на востоке наводнение
Drought in the west
на западе засуха
Liang Province has famine
в Лянчжоу голод
The war with the Wutu
А война с Уну
Has reached a critical moment again
в критической фазе
In this situation
Любая ошибка
If any one matter is mishandled
любое неверное решение
The state faces the risk of collapse
и государство может пасть
Father has reigned for over a decade
Отец правит уже более десяти лет
Whether we should go north
Стоит ли идти в поход
Or not
или не стоит
Or wait for the right time to go north
или подождать подходящего момента
Father understands the stakes better than your son
Отец лучше меня понимает все выгоды и риски
What your son can do
Моё дело
Is to fully cooperate with Father
поддерживать отца
Whatever Father asks your son to do
Что бы вы мне ни велели
Your son will strive to do it well
я исполню со всем усердием
Elder son
Старший
Second son is more tactful than you
младшийто дипломатичнее тебя
Father
Отец
Your son has a few questions
разрешите мне задать несколько вопросов
To ask second brother
младшему брату